Lynn Alden joins us now, founder of Lynn
Alden Investment Strategy. Welcome in,
Lynn.
>> Happy to be here. Thanks for having me.
>> Yes, thanks for joining us. So, you're
famous for the saying, nothing stops
this train. For people who somehow
aren't familiar with that yet, what is
the train? Why can't it stop? And what
do you make of the trajectory for its
acceleration?
>> Uh, so yeah, the train is fiscal
deficits, particularly in the US. Uh,
and it's originally a reference to
Breaking Bad. uh basically the the
inability or the unwillingness to stop
in this you know reapplied here and
basically it's a combination of a couple
things one is uh high degrees of
political polarization in the US it's
very hard to get any sort of meaningful
uh change through uh and then the other
part is mostly demographics and just
decades of accumulated decisions we've
built these entitlement structures that
kind of assume that every generation is
going to be bigger than the prior one
and now of course we we have pretty
topheavy demographics uh we have 40
years of declining industry rates that
that were offsetting ever higher debt
loads. Uh but now that we're over 100%
of debt to GDP and interest rates, you
know, they they they bounced off zero,
they're not falling anymore means that
interest expense is now really a
substantial component of the deficit. Uh
so so even kind of decisions to trim
things here and there uh have trouble
affecting the bigger picture. And so a
lot of this is locked in and it's it's a
macro variable for investors. It's a
macro, you know, it matters for uh
obviously politics. It matters for just
day-to-day um living. Uh but from my
perspective uh mainly what I do is is
focusing on the investment implications
>> and you know under fiscal dominance the
government government spending you know
it can work against the Fed's efforts to
control inflation. Uh what can actually
bring prices under control if if
Washington won't cut the spending?
>> Uh not a ton. I mean that's so the the
kind of the the definition of fiscal
dominance compared to monetary dominance
is that the central bank is kind of in
the back seat here. Their tools are
primarily based around uh accelerating
or decelerating bank lending uh which
works when uh you know unusually high
rates of bank lending are a major
driving force of inflation like like
what we saw in the 70s for example
that's why that particular cure fit that
particular problem. uh but when the when
the government's running 7% of GDP
deficits and when they have so much
accumulated debt that higher interest
rates uh blow out the fiscal deficit
more so than they slow down bank lending
uh their tools just become less
effective. It's not that they have no
impact, but the impact ends up being
mixed compared to just a clean kind of
anti-inflationary medicine that that it
once was when debt levels were lower. Uh
so um you know things like getting oil
flowing you know can help help you know
the get the cost of things down or at
least you know going up more slowly. Um
you know trimming parts of the deficit
where possible can can sometimes address
it. Uh but because it's so locked in uh
it's really not going to stop anytime
soon. And kind of part of it is that
when a when a country gets this
inenddebted, uh it's going to default
one way or another and when they control
the current they when they control the
units for their own liability, um that
default is primarily through purchasing
power uh rather than nominally. And so
kind of like some degree of of inflation
in the basin ends up being um uh
inevitable because they let debt get to
this stage where it's at now. And you
know, you brought up the 70s and and and
you know, uh, policy of the past kind of
makes me think of of kind of maybe
through the 90s with the IT boom,
investment kind of comparing himself to
that and the AI plays a huge part of
that, kind of the core of that. And we
we see figures like Elon Musk saying
we're entering this age of abundance and
and kind of the popular belief in in
Silicon Valley seems to be that we're
going to have this extreme price
deflation. Um, but oftentimes I think
that might be conflated with, you know,
monetary uh or price deflation,
sometimes uh conflated with monetary
deflation. You're someone who's thought
about this for a long time and could
could you help us maybe kind of tease
out those differences there and maybe
where they might be being conflated and
and where you think the limits of what
this AI buildout might be able to
actually help us solve for.
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, one is that the
also the '9s in addition to the tech
boom, they that was also the
demographics boom. So, so peak
demographics in the US meaning kind of
like maximum labor force participation
was in like 1999 or 2000 right right
near the peak as well. So that was like
a multiple multiple factors coming
together to to create that environment.
Um and so but focusing on AI as a topic
basically inflation is a spectrum. Uh so
you know one hand you have things that
are pretty truly scarce you know fine
art waterfront property bitcoin then you
have things that are like a little bit
less scarce but still quite scarce like
gold you know you can make it you can
make more of it slowly um you know
highquality houses um uh energy to
certain extent you know they're labor
intensive they're they're physically uh
constraining in various ways and then we
move across the spectrum you get to
things like grains textiles manufactured
goods semiconductors uh you know with
with the you know multi-deade trend of
Moors law obviously sometimes you have
near-term semiconductor bottlenecks uh
you know uh offshored goods uh and o
over the past several decades obviously
automation uh information technology
offshoring has made us radically better
at making a lot of those things it's
easier to make a t-shirt or a plastic
toy now than it was you know 30 years
ago and so that's helped that that long
end of kind of abundant things stay
cheap even in the even in the face of
money printing
uh and so a lot of the the price gains
were concentrated in the scarce side of
the curve. What AI does is it basically
targets another side. Instead of kind of
suppressing uh you know blue collar
wages and making uh manufactured goods
more abundant, AI comes in and makes a
lot of white collar services just
radically more abundant. you know, it
costs way less to translate something or
edit something uh or or or create, you
know, a poster or something like think
like there's multiple things that just
are way cheaper and more abundant now
because of AI and you know ongoing
improvements there and Mo's law and
everything will keep kind of uh bringing
that down to some uh pretty low level.
Uh and so you're you're you get a it is
true that if that technology continues
to take off as as many of us expect it
will it'll be a deflationary force on
those categories but it doesn't mean
that it slows down money printing uh and
it doesn't mean that it it it radically
reduces the cost of things uh in the
physical world uh or things that are
just very scarce. And so that those are
the assets you want to be long uh even
as other parts do get suppressed. But
also obviously the more abundance there
is the less we feel inflation. So
inflation is still happening in the
monetary sense and how much it impacts
you know the average person will largely
depend on abundance. If you have
negative abundance, so you have war or
you have bottlenecks or constraints or
or technology stagnation, you feel that
money printing more, uh whereas if you
have some sort of offset, uh that then
you generally feel that a little bit
less even though it's still showing up
in the in the scarce end of the the
goods and services curve.
>> So obviously high interest rates make
America's debt more expensive to
finance, but cutting the rates could add
to inflation. So what would force the
Fed to step in and support the
government debt market and what does
that mean for Bitcoin?
>> Well, any sort of acute illquidity would
would make the Fed step in. Uh so um
right now the bond market despite yields
going up has not become truly
disorderly. Um it's still a market
that's able to be made. Obviously
volatility is higher but liquidity is
still fine. um if you have events that
are similar to the the 2022 UK guilt
crisis. So the the the the Bank of
England had a cancel a speech uh about
balance sheet reduction and instead do
emergency temporary QE to to fix their
bond market in in kind of one of the the
greatest ironies. Uh and like that you
know the Fed when when in March 2020
during the kind of the peak of the the
COVID lockdown crash uh it got so bad
the treasury markets went just illquid
just the off ther run securities
literally just kind of broke. Uh and
that's where the Fed had to come in and
to start buying you know with emergency
meetings start buying hundreds of
billions of dollars eventually trillions
of bonds. Um and so you know around the
margins I if it does get illquid at some
point and just starts to generally break
the Fed has to basically step in. Um I
mean they can they can try not to but
then all their other mandates start
breaking apart. So um there's softer
ways they can do it. I mean they have
standing facilities ready uh to provide
liquidity. Um they can potentially ease
bank regulations to let banks be able to
buy more treasuries kind of increasing
their leverage. Um or they can step in
and buy them directly. Obviously that
could that that's hard to do
narrative-wise. Um you know when
inflation's above target. Uh so that
that's kind of one of one of the
hallmarks of later state fiscal
dominance is the Fed finding itself
increasing its balance sheet despite
above target inflation. And even right
now, even as they're increasing rates,
they actually still are mildly
increasing their balance sheet. Uh
they're not buying the long end. Uh but
they're still doing this very gradual QE
uh as part of just their view of
maintaining ample bank reserves and
avoiding some of the liquidity problems
that they faced uh late last year.
>> So gold remains about a quarter below
its record intraday high from January.
What is your outlook for gold right now?
Are you buying more or holding what you
have? And why own gold in addition to
holding Bitcoin?
Uh, so I'm a holder here. I've been a
long-term bull on both gold and Bitcoin.
Um, uh, and you know, since they go up
and down at different times, uh, just
just part of a of kind of a balanced
portfolio. Um, they kind of serve
different purposes for for different
types of tail risks. Um, you know, I I
was a lot more bullish on gold was like
2,000 or less uh, compared to when it,
you know, briefly touched, as you point
out, the inday's high somewhere around
5,000 uh, corrected down to like 4,000
or so. Um, I generally think 4,000 is a
very reasonable number for gold to be
at. Uh, longer term, I'm still bullish
on it. Uh, but I think it still has some
consolidation to do after just how big
of a run it did uh in recent years. Uh,
and basically it's just it it it's a
it's a scarce physical asset. Um, it has
certain advantages over Bitcoin. It has
many disadvantages over Bitcoin. It's
obviously less mobile. It has less true
scarcity. um and you know other other
divisibility or auditing limitations to
it. Um there are certain segments of the
population that like it. There's a you
know there's a physicality I think that
especially in the world of AI um is
interesting to people. So I I just view
it as one of the leading monies out
there, one of the leading kind of liquid
you know bare asset store of value um
alongside Bitcoin.
>> And you know you mentioned that gold and
Bitcoin uh often move separately. Even
though we're seeing the highest
correlation between the two, they still
are not on the same page, it seems. And
many analysts would have expected
Bitcoin to trade down similar to gold uh
with these rising treasury yields. Um
why do you think Bitcoin may be acting
different in this kind of macro
environment um than other kind of
longduration scarce assets like gold? Uh
and what do you think would need to
happen to sort of drive a move back
towards those previous all-time highs
over 100K?
>> Uh so good question. But I mean one is
that uh Bitcoin is a smaller market than
gold by about by about you know an order
of magnitude and it's more volatile. So
it has a a somewhat different holder
profile. I mean you know gold's more
held by sovereigns uh more held by by
older investors uh or partially held in
the form of jewelry. Uh whereas you know
Bitcoin is on average could be held
obviously there's a lot of institutional
holders there's some sovereign holders
uh on average the ownership the retail
ownership profile will skew a little bit
younger than gold. uh is is considered a
little bit more risk uh in in some in
some capacity at least in a portfolio
sense. Um uh and so this the pricing
just kind of works differently.
Sometimes they go up, sometimes they go
down uh together. Uh and in general
fiscal dominance um over the longer term
should drive multiple types of
highquality scarce assets up. That can
include high quality equities. That can
include Bitcoin, gold, anything that's
kind of the leading in its category. uh
as long as the category is still doing
decently. Um as far as what gets Bitcoin
over 100K, I mean that that's a trader
question. I mean obviously it went it
moved quite quickly from I mean
bottoming somewhere around 58K to to
what it is now far higher. Um it's a
smaller move than that to to hit 100. Um
uh and I think it's a combination of
liquidity. Uh I think it's a combination
of just um you know the the the chart
has come in first. They saw that you
know Bitcoin's not going down anymore.
So they they start to get in. Uh if it
starts to build up some momentum, then
momentum traders come in. Uh and and so
you know, a lot already like a lot of
the fast money's out. It's strongly
held. Uh and eventually there there are
things that can attract fast money back.
Uh and but I think that the longer term
backdrop is just that money supplies
around the world are going to keep
growing. Uh the bond markets around the
world are going to keep growing. Nothing
stops those trains. Uh and so there
there there kind of like background
pressure, this rising tide for the best
quality assets, even though just like a
rising tide, you have waves that come in
and out. So you get you get, you know,
surges and corrections. Uh but you still
want to own the highest quality scarce
things and and you know, obviously
Bitcoin is is among the best.
>> So we hit on how AI impacts the macro
picture earlier and and I know you've
talked before about how a peak in AI
stocks could boost Bitcoin. um what
would cause money to rotate out of AI
stocks and and back into Bitcoin rather
than cash or a safer investment?
>> Uh so partially it's it's a it's a uh
view on a riskon situation. So obviously
cash is protective uh whereas someone
you know buying Bitcoin that they
perceive as being kind of near the lows
uh and expecting that it you know could
give another multi-year run. Uh so it's
it's often just a counteryclical
approach. people saying, "Okay, I I you
know, I made huge gains on AI." Um, you
know, at a certain point, the companies
become multi-trillion dollar companies,
and it's hard for them to keep
multiplying uh and get the same kind of
percentage returns that they could when
they were smaller. Uh, and so when they
see Bitcoin, you know, at sub2 trillion
market cap, um, and and generally, you
know, a lot not a ton of fast money in
it. uh there's not traders just like you
know leveraging leveraging to the gills
on Bitcoin in a similar way that they
were kind of ran stocks for example
during the peak memory memory stocks uh
and so uh it just it just becomes a
different risk-on asset or a different
kind of volatile you know tech adjacent
asset uh that some investors will find
interesting and and and just be
interested in getting into in the
counteryclyical sense to be in a less
crowded trade.
Now, you know, spending time in Egypt
means you've experienced firsthand very
different monetary systems from the US.
Has living between the two countries
changed the way you think about um kind
of this broader picture at all? I think
it just gives me more more hands-on
experience. I've been going to Egypt
every year since 2019. I I live
generally for months uh uh each year
there. I mean, right like this currently
official inflation there's 15%. And no
one's talking about it because that's
just that's normal. Like that's the
background. Uh you're kind of like how
in the US if inflation's 2 or 3% not a
ton of people are talking about it. Uh
that's like 15% 10 to 15% in Egypt. Um
and so I mean it's you don't have to
convince an Egyptian why a store of
value is good. Uh you just have to maybe
some discuss which which stores value.
Um uh and it's because when when you're
in a country that doesn't have a robust
stock market like the US does for
Egyptians it's it's generally gold and
real estate uh or even ironically
dollars. Um you know there's some
Bitcoin interest not not a ton on a per
capita basis. Um uh but basically like
emerging markets in general will
generally provide a somewhat more
extreme environment of broken money. uh
and so I think that having some
experience in in both developed and
developing markets uh gives someone a
kind of a broader perspective on the
different ledgers that we have around
the world.
>> You believe in Bitcoin, so why would you
ever sell it? Life happens. An emergency
expense, a new home purchase, or a great
business opportunity. With Salt, you can
access the power of your Bitcoin without
selling. Now with rates starting at 7
12%. The original Bitcoin back lender.
No collateral losses, no rehypothecation
since 2016. Get your exclusive offer at
saltlanding.com/bmtv.
>> Lyn, I wanted to get your thoughts on
stable coins. Um, because obviously it
makes dollars easier to access and move
around the world, but does it actually
strengthen the dollar? Are stable coins
just moving existing dollar demand onto
new rails or is it creating new demand?
>> Yeah, it's a good question. I I think
it's creating some new demand, but that
overall demand is relatively small
compared to existing total demand. Uh
and so the the effect of of
strengthening or solidifying the dollar
is kind of marginal. There there's a
report by city u maybe a year ago or so
that kind of uh looked out at stable
coins through 2030 and had like a bull
base and bare case. I think it's a it
was a reasonable report and they they
categorize different sources of demand.
Uh and some of those as you point out
are are are basically existing demand
for dollars that is like re repurposed
um or or some percentage repurposed and
other times it is generally new demand
for dollars. Basically if if stable
coins can get to places that otherwise
physical dollars or bank accounts would
have had trouble getting uh then that
can that can represent new demand around
the margins. Um or if it if it can you
know solve crossber payment problems uh
in a way that that you know weren't
happening before. It can make various
small businesses and things like that
hold you know marginal stable coin
balances that they might not have
otherwise held in dollars or dollar
assets. Um but you know we're talking
about a very large monetary base and
we're talking about you know hundreds of
billions of potential demand uh in in
the coming years of which some
percentage is new. So these are these
are macroscale numbers but they're not
really gamechanging numbers uh compared
to you know 2 trillion in annual
deficits uh you know the the existing
stock and rate of money supply growth
that we currently have.
>> Now Lynn we're almost out of time but I
got to ask before you go your thoughts
on Japanese yen intervention of course
and Scott Besson's comments um on being
the house and his latest comments
clarifying uh that what he means is that
he has this edge. Do you believe Scott
Bessence Scott Bessant does have an edge
uh intervening in this market here?
>> I mean I think he has an edge. The
question is how big of an edge? Um
basically so between the US and Japan
iron actually especially Japan uh but if
they're working together they've got a
ton of firepower. Uh you know Japan has
well over a trillion dollars worth of
reserves. Uh they also as like a kind of
a nuclear option have their um their
giant pension system and they can choose
to repatriate some of that to sell some
foreign assets and to buy domestic
assets. Basically Japan even though they
have a very high public debt um they've
got a a very positive net international
investment position for their other
assets. They they've got a current
account surplus of of basically
dividends and interest flowing to them
from around the world from all these
investments. Uh and so they actually
have a ton of firepower uh to protect
the yen uh should they want to. So far
they've been, you know, they when it
when it starts to get disorderly
weakening, they come in and they they do
a jolt to kind of break those that are
shorting it on leverage. Um they they,
you know, they they kind of slow that
down. And I mean, they can keep running
that playbook over and over and over for
years. It's it's most a choice of how
large they do it. And when both Japan
and the US generally find that there's a
certain line in the sand that they
prefer to protect, uh they could choose
to protect that pretty aggressively. Uh
you know, not not forever. Uh but the
amount of firepower they have to do it
is pretty immense. So I wouldn't I
wouldn't be too aggressively trading
against it. Um and instead, I mean, I I
I'm long uh Japanese assets that are not
the yen. Uh because I mean, Japanese
corporations are are structurally short
the yen uh in general. Um, uh, you know,
and so I, you know, there's there's I'm
pretty bullish on Japan, even though I'm
not particularly a yen bull. I I think
it's it's more of a consolidation now
with a lot of firepower to kind of
micromanage it.
>> The one and only Lynalden, thanks for
joining us.
Thank you.